Register of the Charles Easton Rothwell papers, 1924-1995
Hoover Institution Archives
- General Subject File, 1946-1979 (Box 55-61)
  - Institute on North Atlantic Pact (Box-folder 57: 23)
  - Iran, clippings (Box-folder 57: 24)
  - Kenya, correspondence, 1968 (Box-folder 57: 25)
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT)
    - Correspondence, 1959 (Box-folder 57: 26)
    - Reports, 1959 (Box-folder 57: 27)
    - Speech (Box-folder 57: 28)
    - Study (Box-folder 57: 29)
  - Naval War College
    - Correspondence, 1955-1966 (Box-folder 58: 1)
    - Catalog of courses (Box-folder 58: 2)
    - Memoranda (Box-folder 58: 3)
  - Presidents' Institute
    - General (Box-folder 58: 4)
    - Correspondence, 1960 (Box-folder 58: 5)
    - Manual (Box-folder 58: 6)
    - Printed matter (Box-folder 58: 7)
    - Report, 1959 (Box-folder 58: 8)
    - Schedule (Box-folder 58: 9)
  - Soviet Union
    - General (Box-folder 58: 10)
    - Clippings (Box-folder 58: 11)
    - Handbook (Box-folder 58: 12)
    - Newsletters (Box-folder 58: 13)
    - Printed matter (Box-folder 58: 14)
    - Speech (Box-folder 58: 15)
    - Writings (Box-folder 58: 16-17)
  - Stanford Research Institute (SRI)
    - General (Box-folder 58: 18)
    - Correspondence, 1949 (Box-folder 58: 19)
    - Memoranda, 1949 (Box-folder 58: 20)
    - Minutes of meetings, 1949 (Box-folder 58: 21)
    - Projects (Box-folder 58: 22-23)
    - Reports, 1949 (Box-folder 59: 1)
    - Study (Box-folder 59: 2)
    - Survey (Box-folder 59: 3)
  - Unions, Socialism Revolution (Box-folder 59: 4)
  - United States
    - General (Box-folder 59: 5)
    - Brochure (Box-folder 59: 6)
    - Bulletin (Box-folder 59: 7)
    - Clippings (Box-folder 59: 8-10)
    - Correspondence, 1948-1969 (Box-folder 59: 11)
    - Handbook (Box-folder 59: 12)
    - Interview (Box-folder 59: 13)
    - Maps (Box-folder 59: 14)
    - Newsletters (Box-folder 59: 15)
    - Press releases (Box-folder 59: 16)
    - Printed matter (Box-folder 59: 17-18)
    - Project (Box-folder 60: 1)
    - Reports, 1946-1975 (Box-folder 60: 2)
    - Speeches, delivered by President Gerald Ford and Herbert Hoover, 1948-1975 (Box-folder 60: 3)
    - Statements (Box-folder 60: 4)
    - Writings (Box-folder 60: 5)
    - World Affairs Council of Northern California (WACNC)
      - General (Box-folder 60: 6)
      - Clippings (Box-folder 60: 7)
      - Correspondence, 1947-1979 (Box-folder 60: 8)
      - Interview (Box-folder 60: 9)
      - Leaflets (Box-folder 60: 10)
      - Memoranda, 1948-1979 (Box-folder 60: 11)
      - Minutes of meetings, 1979 (Box-folder 60: 12)
      - Notes (Box-folder 60: 13)
      - Reports, 1949-1950 (Box-folder 60: 14)
      - Workbook (Box-folder 60: 15)
    - World College West
      - Bulletin (Box-folder 61: 1)
      - Correspondence, 1979 (Box-folder 61: 2)
    - Writings and speeches by others (Box-folder 61: 3-35)
      Includes Charles Rothwell's signature in the cover of the printed copy of an article by David Harris.
- Asia Subject File, 1942-1987 (Box 61-65)
  Articles, bulletins, clippings, correspondence, financial records, maps, memoranda, minutes of meetings, newsletters, news bulletins, notes, pamphlets, press releases, printed matter, reports, telegrams, and writings relating to different Asian countries, Asia Foundation, Pacific Rim Studies Center, and Portland State University, arranged alphabetically by physical form. See also: General Subject File series.
  - General
    - General (Box-folder 61: 36)
    - Article (Box-folder 61: 37)
    - Bulletins (Box-folder 61: 38)
    - Clippings (Box-folder 62: 1)
    - Correspondence
      - Undated (Box-folder 62: 2)
      - 1968
        - February-March (Box-folder 62: 3)
        - April (Box-folder 62: 4)
        - May (Box-folder 62: 5)
        - June-July (Box-folder 62: 6)
        - August-December (Box-folder 62: 7)
      - 1969 (Box-folder 62: 8)
      - 1970-1972 (Box-folder 62: 9)
        Includes letters to the President of the United States and Henry A. Kissinger, Special Assistant to the President for National Security Affairs.
      - 1973 (Box-folder 62: 10)
    - Financial records (Box-folder 62: 11)
    - List of addresses (Box-folder 62: 12)
    - Map (Box-folder 62: 13)
    - Memoranda
      - 1967 (Box-folder 62: 14)
      - 1968 (Box-folder 62: 15)
      - 1970-1973 (Box-folder 62: 16)
    - Minutes of meetings, 1973 (Box-folder 62: 17)
    - Newsletters (Box-folder 62: 18)
    - Notes (Box-folder 62: 19)
    - Pamphlets (Box-folder 62: 20)
    - Press releases (Box-folder 62: 21)
    - Printed matter (Box-folder 62: 22)
    - Proposal (Box-folder 62: 23)
    - Reports, 1958-1973 (Box-folder 62: 24)
    - Research projects (Box-folder 62: 25)
    - Schedule (Box-folder 62: 26)
    - Table of organization (Box-folder 62: 27)
    - Telegrams (Box-folder 62: 28)
    - Writings (Box-folder 63: 1)
    - Miscellany (Box-folder 63: 2)
  - Afghanistan, correspondence, 1969 (Box-folder 63: 3)
  - Bangladesh, clippings (Box-folder 63: 4)
  - Burma, clippings (Box-folder 63: 5)
  - Ceylon, 1969
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 63: 6)
    - Memoranda (Box-folder 63: 7)
    - Miscellany (Box-folder 63: 8)
  - China
    See also: Mills College series.
    - General (Box-folder 63: 9)
    - Bulletins (Box-folder 63: 10)
    - Clippings (Box-folder 63: 11)
    - Correspondence, 1968 (Box-folder 63: 12)
    - Handbook (Box-folder 63: 13)
    - Newsletters (Box-folder 63: 14)
    - Printed matter (Box-folder 63: 15)
  - Hong Kong
    - Bulletins (Box-folder 63: 16)
    - Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 63: 17)
    - Research study (Box-folder 63: 18)
    - Telegrams (Box-folder 63: 19)
  - India
    - Clippings (Box-folder 63: 20)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 63: 21)
    - News release (Box-folder 63: 22)
    - Printed matter (Box-folder 63: 23)
    - Remarks, 1976 (Box-folder 63: 24)
    - Writings (Box-folder 63: 25)
  - Indonesia
    - General (Box-folder 63: 26)
    - Bulletins (Box-folder 63: 27)
    - Clippings (Box-folder 63: 28)
    - Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 63: 29)
    - Printed matter (Box-folder 63: 30)
    - Writings (Box-folder 63: 31)
  - Japan
    - Brochure (Box-folder 63: 32)
    - Bulletins (Box-folder 63: 33)
    - Clippings (Box-folder 64: 1)
    - Correspondence, 1973 (Box-folder 64: 2)
    - Newsletters (Box-folder 64: 3)
    - Notes (Box-folder 64: 4)
    - Printed matter (Box-folder 64: 5)
    - Reports, 1969-1987 (Box-folder 64: 6)
    - Research proposal (Box-folder 64: 7)
    - Writings (Box-folder 64: 8)
  - Korea
    - Article (Box-folder 64: 9)
    - Correspondence, 1955-1969 (Box-folder 64: 10)
    - Report, 1950 (Box-folder 64: 11)
    - Miscellany (Box-folder 64: 12)
  - Malaysia, clippings (Box-folder 64: 13)
  - Nepal, miscellany (Box-folder 64: 14)
  - New Zealand, clippings (Box-folder 64: 15)
  - Pakistan, correspondence, 1969 (Box-folder 64: 16)
  - Philippines
    - Clippings (Box-folder 64: 17)
    - Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 64: 18)
    - News bulletin (Box-folder 64: 19)
    - Newsletters (Box-folder 64: 20)
    - Writings (Box-folder 64: 21)
  - Singapore, clippings (Box-folder 64: 22)
  - Thailand
    - Clippings (Box-folder 64: 23)
    - Correspondence, 1973-1976 (Box-folder 64: 24)
    - Memoranda, 1980 (Box-folder 64: 25)
    - News bulletin (Box-folder 64: 26)
    - Newsletters (Box-folder 64: 27)
    - Printed matter (Box-folder 64: 28)
    - Reports, 1976-1978? (Box-folder 64: 29)
    - Writings (Box-folder 64: 30)
  - Vietnam
    - General (Box-folder 65: 1)
    - Articles (Box-folder 65: 2)
    - Bulletins (Box-folder 65: 3)
    - Certificates and transcripts (Box-folder 65: 4)
    - Clippings (Box-folder 65: 5)
    - Constitution (Box-folder 65: 6)
    - Conversation (Box-folder 65: 7)
    - Correspondence
      - 1970-1974 (Box-folder 65: 8)
      - 1975 (Box-folder 65: 9)
    - Educational programs (Box-folder 65: 10)
    - Guide (Box-folder 65: 11)
    - Memoranda, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 65: 12-13)
    - Military Academy records (Box-folder 65: 14)
    - Minutes of meetings, 1972 (Box-folder 65: 15)
    - Pamphlets (Box-folder 65: 16)
    - Printed matter (Box-folder 65: 17)
    - Reports
      - 1967 (Box-folder 65: 18)
      - 1970 (Box-folder 65: 19)
      - 1972 (Box-folder 65: 20)
      - 1973 (Box-folder 65: 21)
    - Seminar (Box-folder 65: 22)
    - Speech, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 65: 23)
    - Telegrams (Box-folder 65: 24)
    - Writings (Box-folder 65: 25)
    - Miscellany (Box-folder 65: 26)
- Memorabilia, 1945 (Box 66)
  - Academic collar (Box-folder 66: 1)
  - United Nations
    - Charter, typescript and framed (Box-folder 66: 2)
      Includes Draft of the Preamble, status of the final documents as of 22 June 1945, a list, and maps indicating the location of the press where the typesettings in different languages were completed.
    - Flag (Box-folder 66: 3)
- Oversize Material, 1939-1974 (Box 67)
  Brochures, certificates, charts, poem, posters, printed matter, telegrams, and miscellany, arranged alphabetically by physical form. Also includes a certificate in Vietnamese presented to Charles Rothwell at Saigon.
  - Brochure, Mills College, undated (Box-folder 67: 1)
  - Certificates, 1945-1974
    - Hiss, Alger, Secretary General, United Nations Conference on International Organization, 1945 (Box-folder 67: 2)
    - Rothwell, Charles Easton, presented at Saigon, 1974 (Box-folder 67: 3)
  - Charts, undated
    - Institute for College and University Administrators (Box-folder 67: 4)
    - North Atlantic Treaty Organization (Box-folder 67: 5-7)
    - Seating (Box-folder 67: 8-10)
    - Snow Museum of Natural Science, Oakland, program prepared by Nydine Snow Latham, 1961 August (Box-folder 67: 11)
    - United Nations
      - Organs of the United Nations (Box-folder 67: 12)
      - Secretariat (Box-folder 67: 13-15)
    - United States
      - Staff of United States Representative to the United Nations (Box-folder 67: 16)
      - United States delegation (Box-folder 67: 17)
  - Charter, 1945
    - Galley proofs (Chinese, English, Russian and Spanish) (Box-folder 67: 18)
      Includes equivalent text certificates.
    - Printed copies
      - Charter of the United Nations and the Statute of the International Court of Justice (Box-folder 67: 19)
      - Interim Arrangements concluded by the Governments represented at the United Nations Conference on International Organization (Box-folder 67: 20)
  - Lee, Russel V., "Hoover, Herbert" (poem), undated (Box-folder 67: 21)
  - List of names, undated (Box-folder 67: 22)
  - Newsletters, 1958 (Box-folder 67: 23)
  - Posters
    - League of Nations, undated (Box-folder 67: 24)
    - Wartime propaganda poster, 1939 (Box-folder 67: 25)
  - Printed matter, 1945-1956 (Box-folder 67: 26)
  - Telegram, undated (Box-folder 67: 27)
  - Miscellaneous, envelope titled United Nations Committee of the City of New York (Box-folder 67: 28)
- Maps File, 1948 (Map case)
  - Headquarters of the United Nations, undated (Map-case Folder 1)
  - Malaya, 1948 (Map-case Folder 2)
  - Sectional map of San Francisco, undated (Map-case Folder 3)
  - South Vietnam, undated (Map-case Folder 4)
  - Soviet Union, undated (Map-case Folder 5)
- Sound Recordings, 1969-1981 (Cassette cabinet)
  9 sound cassettes relating to Charles Easton Rothwell's trips to Asia, China, and the Middle East; his participation in the anniversary celebrations of Bakersfield College, California; and the debate on American foreign policy and defence between Gerald Ford and James Carter.
  - Energy conference, undated (Phonotape 1)
  - Trips, undated
    - Korea and Vietnam (Phonotape 2)
    - Middle East, 1969 (Phonotape 3)
    - Nepal and Pakistan (Phonotape 4)
    - Pakistan, Asia Foundation (Phonotape 5)
  - Gerald Ford and Jimmy Carter debate on American foreign policy and defense, Palace of Fine Arts, San Francisco, California, 1976? (Phonotape 6)
  - China, 1980 April (Phonotape 7)
    A descriptive narration of the itinerary and sightseeing tours of China.
  - Twenty-fifth Anniversary, Bakersfield College Foundation, 1981 May 5 (Phonotape 8)
    Describes the sights and songs of sixty-eight years history of the growth and development of Bakersfield College.
  - Central Intelligence Agency in Central America, 1984 September 18 (Phonotape 9)
    Lecture by John Stockwell, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida.
- Photographs, 1945-1967 (Photo file)
  141 prints, 13 contact sheets, and 1 album depicting Charles Easton Rothwell with his family and others, United Nations meetings and staff at work, Edward J. Stettinus signing the U.N. Charter, various U.N. projects in different countries, the President's House at Mills College, and the Virginia and Charles Rothwell College Center honoring the Rothwells for their contribution to the growth and development of Mills College and to women's education in the United States.
  - 37 prints of United Nations development projects in various countries, 1953-1954 (Envelope A-B)
  - 23 prints of United Nations meetings and of staff at work, 1945-1954, undated (Envelope C)
    Includes 1 print of Charles Rothwell, 1 print of Dag Hammarskjold, 1 print of Dr. Ralph J. Bunche, 1 print of John Foster Dulles, 1 print of Alger Hiss, 1 print of Edward J. Stettinius signing the United Nations Charter, and 1 contact sheet with print of others.
  - 13 prints and 5 contact sheets depicting Charles Easton Rothwell, undated (Envelope D)
  - 16 prints and 1 contact sheet, 1954, 1961, 1966, undated (Envelope E)
    5 prints of Charles Easton Rothwell with other unidentified individuals; 1 print of Asia Foundation staff; 1 print of the participants of the Fulbright Conference on American Studies, Cambridge University, Great Britain; 1 print of Charles Rothwell giving a speech; 1 print of Charles Rothwell speaking at the United Bay Area Crusade Awards Luncheon, Sheraton Palace Hotel; 1 print of Alexander Van der Hart; 1 print of United States President Franklin D. Roosevelt with others; 1 print of Elmer D. Fagan; 3 prints and 1 contact sheet of the Ninety-eighth commencement of the University of California, Berkeley; and 1 print of Avrshire Farm from the Santa Clara County atlas.
  - 8 prints, 1950s-1960s (Envelope F)
    4 prints of Reed College Fiftieth Anniversary celebrations; 1 print of the staff of National War College; 1 print of Charles Rothwell at the Rotary International annual conference; 1 print of Charles Rothwell addressing California Historical Society annual meeting; and 1 print of the participants of the Far West Fulbright Conference, San Francisco State College.
  - 13 prints and 7 contact sheets of the Rothwell family and others, 1959, 1961, undated (Envelope G)
    6 prints depicting Charles, Virginia and Ann Rothwell going on a trip; 5 prints of Charles and Virginia Rothwell; 1 print of Virginia Rothwell; and 1 print of the Rothwells with an unidentified individual.
  - 22 prints, undated (Envelope H)
    12 prints of the President's House at Mills College; 2 prints of Charles Rothwell and others; 1 print of a pathway in the woods; 1 print of reception at Alderwood Hall; 1 print of a Doctorate of Humane Letters at the Commencement of the University of Santa Clara, California, 1967 (inscribed); 2 prints of United Nations staff at work; 1 print of a United Nations meeting, Jan Smuts speaking; 1 print of the United Nations General Assembly; and 1 print of Easton Rothwell College Center.
  - 1 album of photographs, 1967 (Envelope fI)
    Depicts Charles Rothwell receiving a Doctorate of Humane Letters at the Commencement of the University of Santa Clara, California.
  - 6 prints, 1953-1954, undated (Envelope mJ)
    1 print of Rothwell; 1 portrait of Edward Stettinius (inscribed); 2 prints of United Nations staff at work; 1 print of a United Nations meeting, Jan Smuts speaking; and 1 print of the United Nations General Assembly.
  - 3 photographs of the architectural design of the Virginia and Easton Rothwell College Center, undated (Envelope mK)
- Incremental Materials, 1938-1995 (Box 68-75)
  This later addition to the collection contains published materials, mainly about the United Nations conference in San Francisco in 1945 and disarmament in the 1980s.
  - "Rosa Luxemburg and the German Social Democratic Party: A Dissertation Submitted to the Department of History and the Committee on Graduate Study of Stanford University in Partial Fulfillment of the Requirements for the Degree of Doctor of Philosophy," by Charles Easton Rothwell, 1938 August (Box-folder 68: 1-2)
  - Precis of Committee Proceedings, United Nations Conference on International Organizations, San Francisco, 1945 (Box-folder 68: 3)
  - Communications to Delegations on Conference Organization and Procedure, United Nations Conference on International Organization, San Francisco, 1945 (Box-folder 68: 4)
  - Communications from Executive Secretary to Delegations, United Nations Conference on International Organization, San Francisco, 1945 (Box-folder 69: 1)
  - General, United Nations Conference on International Organization, San Francisco, 1945 (Box-folder 69: 2)
  - Plenary, United Nations Conference on International Organization, San Francisco, 1945 (Box-folder 69: 3)
  - Coordination Committee, United Nations Conference on International Organization, San Francisco, 1945 (Box-folder 70: 1)
  - Commission I: General Provisions, United Nations Conference on International Organization, San Francisco, 1945 (Box-folder 71: 1)
  - Commission II: General Assembly, United Nations Conference on International Organization, San Francisco, 1945 (Box-folder 72: 1)
  - Commission III: Security Council, United Nations Conference on International Organization, San Francisco, 1945 (Box-folder 73: 1)
  - Commission IV: Judicial Organization, United Nations Conference on International Organization, San Francisco, 1945 (Box-folder 73: 2)
  - Commentaries Upon Dumbarton Oaks Proposals (in English and French), United Nations Conference on International Organization, San Francisco, 1945 (Box-folder 74: 1-2)
  - Commentaries Upon Dumbarton Oaks Proposals (in Russian and Spanish), United Nations Conference on International Organization, San Francisco, 1945 (Box-folder 75: 1-2)
  - The United Nations and Human Rights, by James Frederick Green, 1956 (Box-folder 76: 1)
  - The United Nations and Dependent Peoples, by Emil J. Sady, 1956 (Box-folder 76: 2)
  - The Arc of Crisis, by Claude A. Buss, 1961 (Box-folder 76: 3)
  - Grenada Documents: An Overview and Selection, released by the Department of State and the Department of Defense, 1984 September (Box-folder 76: 4)
  - Documents on Disarmament, United States Arms Control and Disarmament Agency, 1979 (Box-folder 76: 5)
  - Documents on Disarmament, United States Arms Control and Disarmament Agency, 1981-1983 (Box-folder 77: 1-4)
  - Origin of the Emblem and Other Recollections of the 1945 U.N. Conference, by Donal McLaughlin, 1995 (Box-folder 77: 5)
- Declassified U.S. Government Records, 1944-1945 (Box 77)
  Formerly security-classified records of the U.S. government, released in full or in part. Includes some interfield, unclassified government records. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover, thereunder chronologically by date of creation.
  - 2016 January release of records, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 77: 6)
    Lists, memoranda, a report, meeting minutes, and a draft resolution, originally from the United Nations and State Department series, particularly boxes 46-47.